Finding Aid for William Randolph Taylor Papers 1918-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Randolph Taylor Papers 1918-1987
Taylor, William Randolph, 1895-
7.5 linear feet
Professor of botany at University of Michigan, curator of algae at the University Herbarium, and biologist with the atomic bomb test program in Marshall Islands in 1946. Correspondence and other papers relating to his scientific interests and activities.
8672 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Taylor (donor no. 1322) and came to the library in 1970. Several additions were made to this accession.
The collection is open for research.
William Randolph Taylor was born in Philadelphia on December 21, 1895. He was educated at the University of Pennsylvania receiving his Ph.D. in botany in 1920. He taught at the University of Pennsylvania becoming professor of botany in 1927. Taylor was throughout his career interested in cytology. He was also deeply involved with microscopy, first with flowering plants and later with algae.
Taylor came to the University of Michigan in 1930 with an appointment as professor of botany and curator of algae in the Herbarium. Simultaneous to his career at Pennsylvania and Michigan, Taylor had worked with the Marine Biological Laboratory in Woods Hole, Massachusetts where he taught the algal course and where he spent most summers from 1917 to 1989.
Taylor excelled as a collector of marine algae, especially seaweed, in British Columbia, New England and eastern Canada, throughout the Caribbean and northern South America, islands off western Mexico to the Galapagos Islands. In 1946, Taylor was appointed senior biologist in "Operation Crossroads" of the Department of Navy and conducted a botanical survey of Bikini and other Marshall Islands in the South Pacific prior to and immediately after the testing of atomic bombs.
Taylor published extensively in his field and was the recipient of many professional honors and citations. He died November 11, 1990.
The Taylor papers are arranged into two principal series; correspondence (1918-1980) and Topical and Subject Papers. Taylor corresponded with most of the significant figures in the field of cytology and algae. The papers do not date beyond 1980 when Taylor left Michigan and retired to the Farlow Herbarium at Harvard in Cambridge.
Subjects:
Algae.; Algae--Marshall Islands.; Atomic bomb.; Bikini Atoll (Marshall Islands); Botany.; Operation Crossroads, 1946.; Scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Taylor, William Randolph, 1895-; University of Michigan. Dept. of Botany.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. University Herbarium.
- Correspondence
  - 1918-1928
    - A-Z, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - 1929-1943
    - A-Z, 15 folders (Box 1)
  - 1941-1950
    - Abbott, Isabella. (Box 2)
    - Allen, G.O. (Box 2)
    - Arctic algae (Box 2)
    - Bartlett, Harley H. (Box 2)
    - Bermuda Station (Box 2)
    - Borgeson, F. (Box 2)
    - Chou, Ruth (Box 2)
    - Conn, H.J. (Box 2)
    - Crousdale, Hannah (Box 2)
    - Dawson, E.Y. (Box 2)
    - Drouet, Francis (Box 2)
    - Fritsch, F.E. (Box 2)
    - Hancock, G. Allan (Box 2)
    - Hancock Pacific Experiments (Box 2)
    - Hodge, Ruth P. (Box 2)
    - Hollenberg, G.J. (Box 2)
    - Howell, John T. (Box 2)
    - Jao, C.C. (Box 2)
    - Kylin, Harold (Box 2)
    - Lewis, Ivey F. (Box 2)
    - Llana, Alfredo (Box 2)
    - McClung, C.E. (Box 2)
    - McCulloch, Irene (Box 2)
    - Maxon, W.R. (Box 2)
    - Packard, Charles (Box 2)
    - Prescott, G.W. (Box 2)
    - St. John, Harold (Box 2)
    - Schramm, J.R. (Box 2)
    - Setchell, W.A. (Box 2)
    - Smith, G.M. (Box 2)
    - Steere, W.E. (Box 2)
    - Stephenson, T.A. (Box 2)
    - Tandy, G. (Box 2)
    - Tseng, C.K. (Box 2)
    - Tuan, H.C. (Box 2)
    - War letters (Box 2)
    - Wu, Su-Hsuen (Box 2)
    - Miscellanea, A-Z (Box 2)
  - 1951-1961
    - A-E, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - F-Z, 10 folders (Box 3)
  - 1962-1967
    - A-L, 10 folders (Box 3)
    - M-Z, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - 1967-1968
    - A-Z, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - 1969-1970
    - A-G, 8 folders (Box 4)
      (include separate folder for John L. Blum)
    - H-Z, 11 folders (Box 5)
      (include separate folder for Smithsonian Institute)
  - 1971-1973
    - Abbott, Isabella A., 2 folders (Box 5)
    - A-Wy, 25 folders (Box 5)
  - 1974-1976
    - A-L, 9 folders (Box 6)
    - Marine Biology Laboratory (Box 6)
    - M-Wy, 8 folders (Box 6)
  - 1976-1980
    - A-W, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - 1970s-1987 (mainly 1981-1987)
    - A-L, 14 folders (Box 6)
      (include separate folders for Bermuda Biological Station; Colinvaux; Croasdale; Herbarium; Irvine)
    - M-W, 12 folders (Box 7)
      (include separate folders for Marine Biological Laboratory; Michigan, University of; Russel Lectureship)
- Topical and Subject Papers
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences, Committee on Hydrobiology correspondence 1951-1955 (Box 7)
  - Atomic bomb tests at Bikini correspondence 1946-1949, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - A.J. Bernatowicz correspondence 1949-1971 (Box 7)
  - F.S. Collins family correspondence 1919-1925 (Box 7)
  - Francis Drouet correspondence 1936-1939 (Box 7)
  - John J. Frederick correspondence 1960-1962 (Box 7)
  - Marshall A. Howe correspondence 1920-1936 (Box 7)
  - Phycological Society of America 1948 (Box 7)
  - Robert T. Wilce correspondence 1953-1959 (Box 7)
  - Woods Hole, Mass., Library Committee 1948-1952 (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea 1948-1968 (Box 8)
- Biographical/personal
  - Biographical obituaries and tributes to WRT in professional journals (Box 8)
  - Speeches and talks to the Azazels and other organizations (Box 8)
  - Letters received about his books and other writings (Box 8)